Guide to the Justin Kimball photographs, 2007-2016 RL.11618
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Justin Kimball photographs
2007-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kimball, Justin, 1961-
RL.11618
2.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 80 prints 13x19 inches
Collection comprises 80 color inkjet prints selected from photographer Justin Kimball's projects, "Elegy" and "Pieces of String." The images were taken between 2007 and 2016 in small towns in Massachusetts, New York State, and Pennsylvania, places whose cultural fabric and economic livelihood have been deeply affected by 20th century deindustrialization. The images in the "Elegy" series depict working class neighborhoods, abandoned buildings and industrial sites, and people gathered on streets and porches, leaning out of windows, and playing ball games. The images in "Pieces of String" are of the interiors of abandoned houses and other buildings, taken as the photographer accompanied his brother, an auctioneer, to these properties; all that is left, as revealed in the images, are the artifacts of the former residents' lives, and the decay of the building and the contents within. All prints measure 13x19 inches. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
13x19 inches
80 prints
Arrangement
The photographic prints are in order as assigned in the artist's inventories.
Biographical Note
Justin Kimball was born in Princeton, New Jersey in 1961. He earned a B.F.A. from the Rhode Island School of Design, and an M.F.A in Photography from the Yale University School of Art. The recipient of a John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation Fellowship, an Aaron Siskind Individual Photographers Fellowship, a Kittredge Educational Grant from Harvard University and the Project Development Grant from Center in Santa Fe NM, he is the author of the monographs Where We Find Ourselves, Center for American Places, Pieces of String, and Elegy (Radius Books), from which the photographs in this collection were selected.
His work can be found in over 40 museum collections, including the J. Paul Getty Museum (Los Angeles), the National Gallery of Art, the George Eastman House, the SF MoMA and the Museum of Fine Arts Boston. Kimball's images have been included in such publications as DoubleTake, Harper's, and Photo Metro.
Kimball has taught photography for more than twenty years and is currently a Professor of Art at Amherst College. He is represented by Carroll and Sons in Boston Massachusetts.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Justin Kimball photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2018 and 2019.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Color inkjet prints, printed on Canson Iinfinity Baryta Photographique paper.
Content Description
Collection comprises 80 color inkjet prints selected from photographer Justin Kimball's projects, "Elegy" and "Pieces of String." The images were taken between 2007 and 2016 in small towns in Massachusetts, New York State, and Pennsylvania, places whose cultural fabric and economic livelihood have been deeply affected by 20th century deindustrialization.
The images in the "Elegy" series depict small town life - working class neighborhoods, streetscapes, abandoned buildings and industrial sites, and people gathered on streets and porches, leaning out of windows, and playing ball games. The images in "Pieces of String" were taken in abandoned houses and other buildings as the photographer accompanied his brother, an auctioneer, to these properties; all that is left, as revealed in the images, are the artifacts of the former residents' lives (including a box labeled "pieces of string too small to save"), and the decay of the building and the contents within.
All prints measure 13x19 inches. A printed inventory and full artist's statement and biography is included with each set of prints.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Abandoned buildings -- Photographs; Abandoned houses -- Photographs; Abandoned houses in art; City and town life -- United States -- History -- 21st century -- Photographs; Community life -- United States -- Photographs; Deindustrialization -- Northeastern States; Deindustrialization -- United States -- Social aspects; Documentary photography -- Northeastern States; Industries -- Northeastern States -- History; Unemployment -- United States -- Social aspects; Working class -- Economic conditions -- Northeastern States; Massachusetts -- Photographs; New York (State) -- Photographs; Northeastern States -- Economic conditions; Northeastern States -- Social conditions; Pennsylvania -- Photographs; Color prints (photographs); Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Kimball, Justin, 1961-
- Elegy, 2012-2016; 1.0 Linear Feet 1 box 40 photographic prints 13x19 inches
  Scope and Contents
  The forty images in this series were taken by photographer Justin Kimball between 2012 and 2016 in unnamed small towns and rural locations in New York State, Massachusetts, and Pennsylvania, places whose cultural fabric and economic livelihood have been deeply affected by 20th century deindustrialization. Chiefly taken in winter, the images document the impact of the decline in the coal, steel, lumber, and paper industries, and farming, and the survivors of this era, showing working class neighborhoods, streetscapes, storefronts, abandoned houses and industrial sites, railroad tracks, and people gathered on streets and porches, leaning out of windows, and playing ball games.
  From the artist's statement: "The pictures I made in these towns are of the people who live there now, their homes, backyards, the streets and the buildings that once supplied the town its livelihood and economy. While the pictures are about a specific region, they also point to a growing invisible, yet ubiquitous, part of the American landscape. The body of work is meant to pose questions about what happens when things get hard; these are questions about struggle, hope and what it is to be human. These are always important questions, but in the wake of the 2016 election cycle they are, if possible, even more critical."
  A printed inventory, full artist's statement, and biography are in the box with the prints.
  - Liberty Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0001)
  - Creek Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0002)
  - Prospect Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0003)
  - Middle Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0004)
  - Oak Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0005)
  - Commerce Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0006)
  - Shenandoah Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0007)
  - Woodlawn Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0008)
  - Clinton Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0009)
  - Lincoln Avenue, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0010)
  - Route 441, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0011)
  - Shamokin Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0012)
  - North Greenbush Road, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0013)
  - Wyoming Avenue, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0014)
  - Echo Farm Road, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0015)
  - Lark Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0016)
  - East Lloyd Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0017)
  - Country Road 143, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0018)
  - Cliff Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0019)
  - Bliss Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0020)
  - South Broad Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0021)
  - Niagara Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0022)
  - Ethel and Main Stretts, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0023)
  - Coal Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0024)
  - Old Highway 5, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0025)
  - West Frack Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0026)
  - Highway 5, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0027)
  - Way Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0028)
  - Spruce Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0029)
  - Route 394, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0030)
  - State Road 211, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0031)
  - Mohawk Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0032)
  - Mount Vernon Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0033)
  - Centre Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0034)
  - East Water Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0035)
  - Race Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0036)
  - Market Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0037)
  - South River Avenue, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0038)
  - East Mill Street, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0039)
  - Stateline Highway 5, 2012-2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11618-P-0040)
- Pieces of String, 2007-2011; 1.0 Linear Feet 1 box 40 photographic prints
  From the artist's statement:
  "For four years Justin Kimball photographed in abandoned homes, hotels and buildings in the Northeastern United States. For much of this work he accompanied his brother Doug, an auctioneer, into the houses of the deceased or dispersed. While Doug cleared these spaces of items for potential resale, Justin sought within them the evidence of an individual's life. Photographing 'the smallest objects (a note, a box of hair pins, a stain on a pillow),' Kimball re-imagines their existence and relationship to the absent owners. 'I use the camera's descriptive power and the photographic illusion of truth to create the narrative and inspire feelings about its subject. The resulting photographs are my perception of what happened in those spaces: Who lived there? What was hidden and what was seen?' Kimball's color photographs from this body of work are explorations of the minutiae of everyday life - a contemplation of our brief and humble legacies before they are cleaned up and cast to the wind."
  - Forest Road, garden record, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0041)
  - Holyoke Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0042)
  - Florence Road, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0043)
  - Adler Avenue, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0044)
  - Church Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0045)
  - Forest Road, matel, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0046)
  - Pavilion Avenue, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0047)
  - Washburn Avenue, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0048)
  - Federal Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0049)
  - Lyons Hill Road, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0050)
  - 5th street, attic, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0051)
  - Forest Road, bedroom, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0052)
  - South Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0053)
  - Green Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0054)
  - Route 2, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0055)
  - Center Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0056)
  - Lewis Drive, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0057)
  - Main Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0058)
  - Mount View Road, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0059)
  - Adler Avene, 2nd floor, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0060)
  - Washington Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0061)
  - Cecile Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0062)
  - Spring Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0063)
  - Willow Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0064)
  - River Road, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0065)
  - Lewis Drive, hallway, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0066)
  - Ocean House Road, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0067)
  - Lewis Drive, bathroom, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0068)
  - Dublin Drive, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0069)
  - Washburn Avenue, bedroom, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0070)
  - Park Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0071)
  - Lyons Hill Road, floor, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0072)
  - Mount View Road, basement, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0073)
  - Gale Avenue, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0074)
  - Main Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0075)
  - Mount View Road, attic, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0076)
  - Federal Street, garage, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0077)
  - Grove Street, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0078)
  - Forest Road, back door, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0079)
  - Adler Avenue, bed, 2007-2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11618-P-0080)